66. Paul Gauguin. Paul Gauguin was a French artist who is now seen as one of the founders
of modern art. He began painting as an impressionist, but he grew tired of that style. He evolved
toward the use of figures and clear, outlined blocks of color. Indeed, he is best known
for his use of flat color. He used images and symbols from his travels in exotic lands,
such as Martinique, Panama, and Tahiti, giving his paintings a sense of mystery. Gauguin lived
in Europe for most of his early life. He married a Dutch woman and had five children with her.
But he left European styles behind early in his art career. He grew tired of classical
European perspective and subtle coloring. Influenced by Japanese prints and folk art,
he began to move towards Closinism. Closinism is a painting style named after a glass technique
in which colored glass is put into blocks or cells to create a picture. Closinism painting
uses bold colors and black outlines to define objects clearly. Gauguin's painting, The
Yellow Christ, is considered the greatest example of a Closinist work. In 1891, a frustrated
Gauguin left Europe and sailed to the tropics. He lived most of the rest of his life in Polynesia.
He painted many of his most famous works there, including Where Do We Come From?, What Are
We?, Where Are We Going?, which many believe to be his masterpiece. His works from this
time in his life depict Polynesian life, usually from a biased point of view that shows Polynesia
as a paradise, and also use a variety of religious symbols. Gauguin may not have had
a conventionally successful life. He never made much money, and his family fell apart.
However, the distance he put between himself and his culture certainly paid off in his art.